[SPEAKER_01]: I was thinking about the Buddha's practice before he was enlightened, because that kind of indicates what you need to be doing, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says that in a few suttas, what he was doing before, not just ascetic practices, but things that actually...
[SPEAKER_00]: Leading up to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leading up to his attempts... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...towards nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things that really help.
[SPEAKER_01]: And...
[SPEAKER_01]: One of those was that two kinds of thoughts, sutta, where he divided his thoughts into two classes, the unbeneficial and the beneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, when he saw the unbeneficial, when an unbeneficial thought arose, he saw that it wasn't for his own good or the good of others.
[SPEAKER_01]: It didn't lead to freedom, peace.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, just that kind of seeing the danger of those types of thoughts, that is when they subsided and ended, just by contemplating the danger, thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, but the thing is, that's the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: The root of the problem
[SPEAKER_00]: is a thought, a dhamma, a mental image, affected with craving, affected with desire, affected with ill-will, affected with hindrances, put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in order to... in order to be able to see the problem on that level, to recognize that the problem is indeed on the level of a mental image,
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to start practicing withdrawal from everything, all the behaviors that depend, that exist on the basis of corrupted mental image.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's why, again, in like in all the suttas and whenever the Buddha was describing the whole idea of that gradual training, is he has to start with virtue,
[SPEAKER_00]: has to start with uncompromising principles around the wholesome behavior, choices, responsibility, recognizing your intentions as the kind of one of the decisive factors whether things will be wholesome or unwholesome.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, virtue, sense restraint, all that purification is just to bring you
[SPEAKER_00]: Closer and closer to actually recognize that source for yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, everybody can wrap their head around idea that, oh, yeah, the thought is the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you don't really... that... that... that information does not sink in, does not become knowledge or understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can... you can try and address your thoughts all you want.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can manage them, you can counter them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if your behavior is not dried up
[SPEAKER_00]: From all the unwholesome choices you're making, on account of all the corrupted images, it will make no difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, as I said before, it's like trying to... like cleaning your skin, while the festering infection remains untreated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like, you could make it look clean, but it's actually as infected.
[SPEAKER_00]: In a dirty environment, completely dirty.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, and the whole purification of the gold similar in the suttas,
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't start by picking up the microscopic impurities with tweezers and stuff, like while there is still coarse filth floating in the same liquid.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to start by removing that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, of course, the whole purpose of sensory strength training
[SPEAKER_00]: Self-training, in terms of virtue and responsibility, we often talk about, is to reveal to you that, yeah, your mental images are the root of the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: Have you grasped signs and features of the beautiful, out of the habit, out of the dependence on desire, out of seeking the pleasures, or have you not grasped signs and features of what your mind is trying to present you with?
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you do reach that level, you recognize, oh, at this point here,
[SPEAKER_00]: All I need to do is recognize whether an arisen mental image is partaking in any of the hindrance or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if it isn't, I'm blameless and I'm burdenless and I have no...
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't need to do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't even need to keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't even need to be restrained.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you will be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the reason for breaking the precepts, the reason for the lack of the restraint is you already have taken up or allowed
[SPEAKER_00]: These mental images of the corrupt nature, rooted in greed, aversion, distraction, doubt, hindrances, you are allowed them to be on that internal center stage that kind of determines, pushes your intentions, pushes your choices and all that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And all of that is not something you did in the past.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, you know, yesterday I allowed those images and that's why today this is happening.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yesterday you might have allowed the wrong images,
[SPEAKER_00]: You grasp the signs and features carelessly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You allow them to proliferate.
[SPEAKER_00]: You fuel them to proliferate more.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if that's still happening today, it's because today there is still connection to the same images on the same level.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are still doing it, in other words.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do you then stop?
[SPEAKER_00]: And then people would try to stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, they read the suttas like that and then they think, okay, I must get rid of these images.
[SPEAKER_00]: I must get rid of the mind
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why we always say, first and foremost, you don't act out of those images.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know what you will not do.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the images is not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just you willingly picking up the implications of those images, the signs and features, the nimittas, as the suttas often say.
[SPEAKER_00]: And as we said, having seen, sight with the eye, heard, sound with the ear, goes for all the senses, a skilled monk does not pick signs and features.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, he does not allow, does not focus on signs and features implicit of desire, implicit of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_00]: Implicit of distraction, of the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the signs and features of the image... the images, eh... whose signs and features you're not picking up, they remain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you want to get rid of the bait, you're going to be reaching out and falling for the bait.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind of sensuality, for example, and sensual thoughts that want to come up, as I said, you want to unfocus from them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not by focusing on something else, which might help, as I said in the beginning, it might help if you just try and think about something else, but you have to be careful whether that whole project of, or I think about the opposite, is rooted in trying to get rid of the entire mind of centrality, because you don't want to suffer, you don't want to experience the discomfort of the pressure that it exerts over you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or is it rooted?
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm not trying to get rid of the mind of centrality.
[SPEAKER_00]: To kill it, to strangle it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm trying to teach it that that which it wants is actually undesirable.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it doesn't know that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That animal doesn't know that sensuality is actually like burning coals.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to convey that to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't convey to it if your immediate, like a knee-jerk reaction is pressure of sensuality, get rid of it, get rid of it, get rid of it, think the opposite, get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not the middle way.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's now going completely the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there's pressure of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha says he doesn't...
[SPEAKER_00]: The Buddha doesn't say, oh, he gets rid of that mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: He says he doesn't grasp the signs and features that are trying to enter the center stage.
[SPEAKER_00]: As we said before, it's like you already know at the back of your mind, peripherally speaking, if the mind is affected with hindrance, with doubt, if there is like a lingering ill will or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it wants to.
[SPEAKER_00]: It pushes you to crystallize images and thoughts that
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what you don't do.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will not allow the crystallization of these vague pressures, because I already know what will crystallize itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: In what way those thoughts would crystallize themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: In the directions that it wants to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, the mind wants to go in those directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's trying to send you in that way, but you are the one that gives that final input of grasping the signs and features.
[SPEAKER_00]: By grasping them, in other words, means allowing them to basically crystallize and take the center stage, and then you want to deal with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you already fell for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's my point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the Buddha divided the thoughts, the mental images, into two classes, that's already included.
[SPEAKER_00]: Dividing the two... all of the thoughts into two groups implies already, see, this ambiguous
[SPEAKER_00]: Pressuring images that are not quite as crystallized, well, that's already recognized as an unwholesome thought, because you already know where it would crystallize you towards, to put it that way.
[SPEAKER_00]: But people usually don't see that as a thought.
[SPEAKER_00]: They take it for granted.
[SPEAKER_00]: They take this pressure of something, of sensuality, of real will, and then thoughts, fully crystallized, of sensual thoughts, and then try to counter them, in order to get rid of the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, that sutta we often mention in Anguttara Nikaya, that how does one free himself from hindrances?
[SPEAKER_00]: It wasn't about changing the mind, or replacing it, or getting rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It was about learning how to attend through what the mind is trying to present you with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the mind is pushing these thoughts to forefront.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your responsibility is to not allow them to take the center stage and proliferate them further, but instead see through
[SPEAKER_00]: What's being pushed at you, see where it comes from, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it comes from the mind already affected by desire, already affected by a will.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when the mind is pressuring you with negative states, to put it that way, you already know what thoughts would develop if you start proliferating them and allowing signs and features to take the center stage.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, instead, by not doing that, but at the same time not trying to get rid of that mind out of aversion, you are actually dealing with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are leaving your own mind
[SPEAKER_00]: That wild animal, you're leaving, you're making it stay with its own pressure, with its own thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't fall victim of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't act out of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't mask and blur the waters by getting involved with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, it sort of sinks in for the mind itself, that these thoughts are unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the only reason mind engages with sensuality, mind pressures you towards acts of sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's because you want to get rid of those unpleasant thoughts of sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same with ill-will, same with any hindrance.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it involves you, which basically, in return, actually, just perpetuates that dependence of your own mind on you acting out, on you blurring the lines, so that you can ignore the real problem, which is, whether you engage with sensuality or not, whether you engage with ill-will or not, presence of those pressures
[SPEAKER_00]: And signs and features of lust, aversion, distraction, hindrances, it's already unpleasant in and of itself, which is exactly why the mind wants you to do something about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you give in to that, you're baited, you're hooked.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you doing something about it, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: managing, is just inadvertently fueling it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You might, in a worldly sense, you might, sure, like, develop a better skill in management of it, so you might not be as
[SPEAKER_00]: As careless, as proliferated, as sort of unwholesome as before.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, fundamentally, you are still accepting it, accepting that role, accepting that involvement, accepting that saṅkhara, that activity.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, fundamentally, that's all Mara wants.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, like, you have people that just carelessly go to sensuality.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you have people that say no to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they don't discern the middle way, so then they just try to deny the whole picture.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, mara still has them, as the suttas describe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that means like, okay, so, sure, you can be engaging carelessly, or try and shun the bait, and dismiss the whole thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Either way, underneath it all, the problem remains, and you are involved, and you're fueling it inadvertently through your involvement.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you see those hindrances,
[SPEAKER_01]: There's directions where the mind wants to go into, and you don't go in there.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can see them as arisen inclinations.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know those directions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, when the mind is pressured, you don't need to allow images to crystallize to know where it wants to take you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already know.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the point is to train yourself to keep recognizing that you already know where the mind is inclining.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that inclination is real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's already a mental image.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, in the beginning, you think mental images are only things that you can see, hear, smell, taste, touch.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you start practicing sensory strain.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, the threshold for what defines a mental image increases.
[SPEAKER_00]: You recognize, okay, even the thoughts and vague sense emotions and stuff, they're all real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're mental images.
[SPEAKER_00]: But see now, even these directions of your disrupted mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a mental image, as real as such, on that level.
[SPEAKER_01]: It is activated.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's activated and it is an image that you would have already taken up the signs and features from, of.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you won't be able to just stop the signs and features of these subtle directions, pressures, ambiguities, unless you would have practiced the same non-taking of signs and features of whatever the mind tries to serve you with.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the practice, you know, how many times we say endurance on the right level, the khanti, that the patience in regard to debate, that the mind is putting in front of you, like, take it, take it, take it, it will help both of us.
[SPEAKER_00]: Obviously, in order to be able to stay on that right level of not taking the... not allowing the center stage for the images that come out of that already wrongly inclined mind, can only be developed if you would have
[SPEAKER_00]: Withdrawn yourself from the coarser forms of the same principle, which is misbehavior by body, unbeneficial behavior by body, by speech.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you need to work that way up, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, once those unwholesome inclinations have settled down, the mind actually got the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Means the mind is getting the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And starts to relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then even those pressuring directions that you... they would have been quite confining in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, first time you start saying no to your desires, it just feels like you're fully trapped.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, inside out, it's just all of it feels like it's against you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just because you're so used to in escaping it through movement of activation, of acting by body, acting by speech, acting by mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why generally, like, when people hear about sense restraint,
[SPEAKER_00]: Celibacy, withdrawing from sensuality, it's like the suttas, when it says, oh, Master Gautama, that sounds like an abyss to a householder.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, as much as you would be shocked and frightened by discovering a massive, bottomless abyss right in front of your next step, that's how shocked and frightened people are when they hear they have to give up the sense desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then he was praising the Buddha's teaching how those who follow the dhamma seem to overcome that and then overcome the desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they are not afraid of it anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sutta that I mentioned, that once the... those unwholesome inclinations, the mind's unwholesome inclinations have settled down, subsided, due to his understanding of it, then he lives still diligently, but then a wholesome thought arises, and he knows that... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he knows that if he thinks about this, it goes in that direction, there's nothing that can go wrong.
[SPEAKER_01]: It won't lead him... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Later on, even that becomes unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: See, when you would have cultivated the whole... when you recognize the direction is not unwholesome, you don't have to act out of that assumed sense of duty, but I still must deal with this.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You only need to deal with thoughts that are rooted in hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, once you start recognizing that they're not, but it's not something you decide.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, now I will start
[SPEAKER_00]: Changing this practice as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: I will start...
[SPEAKER_00]: I will begin now calming even my wholesome thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: That becomes apparent when the time for that comes.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is no more unwholesome directions coming up from your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: When every thought that comes up, the center stage of an unwholesome pressure is simply... doesn't even exist as a possibility to engage with.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you realize, okay, now I could relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't even have to keep an eye on this, because even my own mind now, that animal, prefers
[SPEAKER_00]: The beneficial thoughts over the unbeneficial, how it used to be.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's literally the simile of the... in the suttas of those cows, when they used to stray and wander into the other people's crops.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, constantly you had to know, I'm not allowing them to feed there.
[SPEAKER_00]: But after a while, they learn.
[SPEAKER_00]: The animals learned to not go there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you recognize that, and then it's like, okay, now I don't need to constantly...
[SPEAKER_00]: I can even lay down and sleep and relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: When I wake up, they're still where they should be, because they don't want to go into other people's crops.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's not up to you to decide when that will happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Up to you is to not allow the center stage, not grasp the signs and features of the of the pressuring thoughts, not leak towards the unbeneficial directions on account of your physical or verbal behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then the mind
[SPEAKER_00]: When it stops kicking and screaming in face of the seeming confinement of restraint, we'll calm down and prefer it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And once it prefers it, you realize now I can trust it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can trust it more.
[SPEAKER_00]: Maybe still not fully, if you are unsure, but it has shown me that it does prefer renunciation, because it's factually better.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has shown me that it does prefer friendliness and non-ill will, because it is factually better.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're seeing the danger in those unwholesome thoughts and you're staying clear of that, the inclinations.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that whole contemplation of that inclination is unwholesome, that inclination is going to lead to trouble.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That already is... this direction, this type of thinking, this inclination to think and to catch any
[SPEAKER_01]: Unwholesome inclination is a good inclination.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can you can actively think about it as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I said to people, like, when they feel like they need to practice meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, yes, but you need to understand what meditation is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if you just keep practicing calming, because your mind gets disturbed, as in artificial calming through methods and techniques, that's not uprooting the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just sort of numbing it down.
[SPEAKER_00]: You really want to practice meditation in a sense of finding a place where you're not disturbed in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, instead of just trying to blindly calm your mind because it bothers you, you need to recognize why is it disturbed in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why does the mind want to disturb things and, above all, why do I still give in to that?
[SPEAKER_00]: And no amount of calming will magically resolve that for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only frequently thinking it, recollecting your virtue or lack of thereof,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, making an effort to improve that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, sit for meditation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sit in the meditation and then think why does your mind get disturbed?
[SPEAKER_00]: And really clarify that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the sutta tells you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it engages with unbeneficial thoughts.
[SPEAKER_00]: It goes in that direction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter if you're a monk or a layman.
[SPEAKER_00]: The unbeneficial thoughts are thoughts rooted in greed, aversion, delusion, in five hindrances.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the sole reason for disturbance for dukkha, for everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you still cultivate them, it doesn't matter what you do on top of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you do start to recognize that, you can actively then think about the danger, the unbeneficialness of these thoughts, like remind yourself, just so that your mind gets to hear it more and more, gets to see, gets to be reminded of those very perceptions that deep down even that wild animal can relate to.
[SPEAKER_00]: And get to see that safety that it's now abiding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's what's going to become apparent afterwards.
[SPEAKER_00]: The safety is not going immediately, because it's just... everything is, as I said, seems confining and seems like going against the grain, because it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you do that long enough, then you do recognize what's right in front of you.
[SPEAKER_00]: When this has been abandoned, the unbeneficial thoughts allowing the center stage for signs and features of the unsuitable kind, you abandon that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not allowing it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't matter the pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remain basically recognizing where that threshold of your careless input is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, one day, you just recognize what's there when that picture is maintained.
[SPEAKER_00]: And what's there is, oh, an undisturbed mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Loads of the space of a trained animal.
[SPEAKER_00]: Trust, as well, that, oh, actually, I can relax, because I do see that if this is the environment maintained, animal cannot go into other people's pastures.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the one who used to inadvertently open the gate and let them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they were just pressuring me too much, and I didn't... Mentally, I wasn't capable of, like, dealing with it, in a sense of, you know, somebody pressures you to take this, take or give it to me, and harasses you for it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you realize, well, it doesn't matter the amount of pressure they put on me.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'm the one who chooses to act, because I don't want to be living with that pressure.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like, well, that's... that's... you give in to the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: But noticing that's what's there, then,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's a safe place.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then your efforts become verified, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_00]: All your efforts of withdrawal, enduring on the right level, not grasping signs and features, not proliferating, not acting out, get confirmed.
[SPEAKER_00]: That it works, because you recognize, oh, this is a factual safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: That I arrived not through doing this or that technique or practice and then just magically got revealed, but simply through withdrawing from everything that was obstructing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And knowing clearly that is an obstruction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: That is an obstruction.
[SPEAKER_01]: And withdrawing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then you will know even more clearly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you will start noticing even subtler obstructions that you might not have noticed before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now you have actually a palpable reference as to, oh, this is the factual safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, right away, you'll see anything that contradicts that safety or threatens it and anything that doesn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then that gives you even more confidence in practice and the path.
[SPEAKER_01]: The recognition, that's jhāna, don't you realize?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's the peace, the joy, the pleasure of... Yeah, I don't want to use those terms, because people have all these preconceived notions already.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you say jhāna, ah, jhāna, whatever my idea of jhāna is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yeah, factually, that is jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but you can see what jhāna means there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, jhāna means what the Sutta says it means.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means thorough, complete withdrawal from the five hindrances and everything that's unbeneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Understanding it all.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a complete understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Clarity that arises on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm completely safe.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I can, actually.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, this safety that arrived not through me fabricating it through one pleasure or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: It arrived through withdrawing from any and all dependence on pleasure of the senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Through withdrawing the mind from it, recognizing the the the profound inherent unbeneficialness of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then finding safety in withdrawal from that, and then sinking in.
[SPEAKER_00]: That sinks into your mind as well, that knowledge.
[SPEAKER_00]: So now it's effortless for you, because the mind prefers it as well.